Good morning. Today's דף daf is ט. tet. We pick up with
המשנה חזרה ומדברת. Hamishna chazera umidaberet. I understand we read it yesterday.
We'll just start again quickly today. We move from describing the ritual
of the סוטה Sotah to talking
about this sort of sense of divine justice and that all the
things that were done to the סוטה Sotah are paralleling the types
of acts that she did or she might have done in her
seduction
and in her adultery. Of course, what he is willing to point
out and then that's when leads to general motto of the whole
idea of מידה כנגד מידה, mida keneged mida, measure for measure. See,
Shakespeare stole it from the גמרא. Gemara. So and the point being
that a person is judged in this world, God brings about events
in this world that
basically are appropriate payback for the deeds that a person has done.
So it's worth pointing out a few things just about this and
this framing. And there's a lot of אגדתא Aggadeta that we have
to look at. But one or two things to point out is
number one is that once again we're assuming that she's guilty and
we're reading this whole ritual not as a way of getting her
to confess or not as whatever, but it's specifically like we are
degrading her in public and as payback for what she did. It's
a public shaming and it's a presumption of guilt because all of
this happens until the actual water, all of that happens without knowledge
of whether she's guilty or not. Right? So it's one thing to
say מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida about the water, it's another
thing to say it about all of the ritual leading up to
the water. There's again this somehow presumption of guilt. I should by
the way mention in that regard that the whole idea about ripping
the garment, תוספות Tosafot points out that you would do a similar
thing before giving lashes to a person is you would rend garments.
Now again it could be connected to the idea while you gotta
give lashes directly to the body, you don't want to do it
through the clothes. But תוספות Tosafot actually points out that this is
seen as a form of the punishment that בית דין Beis Din
is imposing. Wait, the guy who got lashes we know is guilty.
So again that's exactly the point. Seeing this ritual again starting with
this whole presumption of guilt. How are we looking at this as
a punishment as opposed to a way of identifying whether or not
she's guilty? The other interesting thing to note about this whole מידה
כנגד מידה mida keneged mida is,
to some degree, right, it is like the whole question about this
trial by ordeal, like this divine thing, a miracle here that's supposed
to take place to prove whether or not she's innocent or guilty.
So to one degree we sort of contained it by a number
of things, you know, by trying to get her to admit as
soon as possible, you know, trying to get her to confess. We
sort of naturally treated it as evidence. So if it proves it
then it would override what witnesses said otherwise. Remember that discussion? So
in a way almost like downplaying it, not focusing on it and
so on. Also ways of explaining if it doesn't work, maybe because
he had merit, maybe because she had merit, maybe because she sinned.
So there's one way of dealing with this just like
downplaying that. The other way is heightening it, you know, sort of
its מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida and yeah, like God is
going to here punish her not just in terms of the מידה
כנגד מידה mida keneged mida that the כהן Kohen is doing, but
in terms of the effect of the water. So sort of heightening
that sense about this is
exactly... by the way,
again the more that you can, well whatever, I'll just leave that.
Okay. So that's like another interesting thing about what we do by
sort of focusing on the מידה כנגד מידה. mida keneged mida. And
then I guess the final thing to say is half of this
מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida is done through human agents, right?
The other half is done through a miracle, right? But then when
we sort of broaden it to the מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged
mida that God does, it's all sort of directly through God, not
through human beings sort of consciously imposing punishments on people מידה כנגד
מידה. mida keneged mida. It's sort of all which God brings down.
Which sort of also sort of makes the כהן Kohen and makes
this whole ritual and makes everybody sort of just like an agent
of God, you know, sort of a vehicle through which God is
working, which also is important because how do you do this thing
to this woman and maybe she is innocent or whatever. So it's
interesting how it sort of changes the sense of how things are
playing out by heightening
the God's acting here in the מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida
element. So let's with that in mind let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says the following. There's
a משנה Mishna we'll start. במידה שאדם מודד כך מודדין לו. Bemida
she'adam moded kach modedin lo. The same measure a person measures out
in this world, they measure out for him up in heaven. היא
קישטה את עצמה לעבירה המקום ניולה. Hi kishta et atzma la'avera Hamakom
nivla. She beautified herself for sin, God disfigured her.
Of course again as I was saying a minute ago, God and
the working through the כהן, Kohen, right? So that's how God disfigured
her. היא גילתה את עצמה לעבירה המקום גילה עליה. Hi gilta et
atzma la'avera Hamakom gila aleha. She revealed herself, God
is revealing her, but again the כהן Kohen presumably through rending the
garments. בירך התחילה בעבירה תחילה ואחר כך הבטן. Beyerech hitchila ba'avera techila
ve'achar kach habeten.
She began with the thigh and then the stomach. and then the
stomach, meaning, you know, sometime, so sometimes, by the way, בטן beten
is used, you know, or רחם rechem is used as a euphemism
for vagina or whatever, but anyway, maybe it also just means externally
as we'll see, the man supporting his weight on her, we'll get
to that in the גמרא. Gemara. לפיכך תלקה הירך תחילה ואחר כך
הבטן. Lefichach tilakeh hayerach techilah ve'achar kach habeten.
So therefore it starts first with the thigh because it says ויתן
ה' את ירכך נופלת ואת בטנך צבה. veyiten Hashem es yerecheich nofeles
ve'es bitneich tzavah. Okay,
and we'll talk about the order in the גמרא. Gemara. Now we're
finally getting to not the act of the כהן, Kohen, whether or
not she's guilty, but the act of the water when she is
guilty, and it's all getting wrapped together in the same package. Okay?
ושאר כל הגוף לא פלט, Veshar kol haguf lo palat, and don't
worry, the rest of the body isn't going to escape punishment either.
We're getting to go to like the end, right? I mean, like
what about the whole... I know, so the... it is interesting, but
on the other hand it's nice. Often we complain in the מסכתות
masechtos that we start, we get all these digressions and technical points.
Here you have a whole little package. Here's the way it works
from the beginning, here's what happens, and here's sort of the theological
explanation of what's happening. But again, notice how this packaging is very
much the assumption of guilt. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says the following.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, אף על גב דמידה בטלה במידה
לא בטלה. af al gav d'midah batlah b'midah lo batlah.
Even though people we no longer have, this is clearly what he
means by context, we no longer have actual court-imposed punishments now that
there's no longer a בית דין Beis Din of, you know, twenty-three,
and we you know we no longer דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, people
are still getting paid back measure for measure for what they do,
you know, by God. That the heaven, God is still making sure
that that proper punishment is meted out. דאמר רב יוסף D'amar Rav
Yosef because רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, וכן תני רבי חייא, vechein
tani Rabbi Chiya, מיום שחרב בית המקדש אף על פי שבטלה סנהדרין,
miyom shecharav Beis Hamikdash af al pi shebatlah Sanhedrin, סנהדרין Sanhedrin from
the time the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was destroyed even though we
no longer had a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. arba misos
lo batlu. We the the four modes of execution did not cease.
So גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean? והא בטלו, Veha batlu,
they did cease. אלא דין ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. Ela din arba
misos lo batlu. Fine, the court-imposed execution ceased but the judgment, the
justice that God metes out, that never stopped. Okay,
no, why the דין? din? No, I don't think it means sentencing.
I think it means רש"י Rashi says דין שמים שהיא דוגמתו, din
Shamayim she'hidugmato, the divine justice that's meted out. Okay, מי שנתחייב סקילה,
Mi shenitchayev sekilah, if somebody was had to be stoned, so what's
going to happen to him? או נופל מן הגג, o nofel min
hagag, he'll either fall off a roof, או חיה דרסתו, o chayah
darastoh, or an animal will trample him. Now how's that similar to
סקילה? sekilah? Because after they stoned him they pushed him, right, they,
you know, right, I mean not after, before, they pushed him first
off a cliff and then they put the stone on him and
רש"י Rashi says when an animal like attacks you, he attacks somebody,
he knocks him to the ground.
Where were we? מי שנתחייב
שריפה, Mi shenitchayev sereifah, somebody who's deserving of being burnt, which they
would pour molten lead down the throat, but actually it's easier to
get a normal type of a שריפה. sereifah. או נופל בדליקה, o
nofel b'deleykah, either he's consumed in a fire, או נחש מקישו, o
nachash makisho, or bitten by a snake so the poison is like
a fire, burns. מי שנתחייב הריגה, Mi shenitchayev harigah, which is execution
by sword. או נמסר למלכות, o nimsar lamalchus, either he gets he
gets punished by the by the government, which the the secular, the
Roman authorities, that would execute by the sword. או ליסטין באין
עליו, o listin ba'in alav, or bandits attack him by the sword.
מי שנתחייב חניקה, Mi shenitchayev chanikah, somebody who was deserving of getting
executed by being strangled. או טובע בנהר, o toveiah banahar, either he
drowns in a river, so he, you know, drowns by by asphyxiation,
או מת בסרוכני, o meys b'saruchni, or he dies in a certain
type of a choking death, also a respiratory death. תניא, Tanya, actually
it's interesting in terms of the Romans,
in terms of crucifixion, they actually kill the person through asphyxiation. Oh
really? That's interesting. Okay, interesting. תניא האי רבי אומר, Tanya hai Rebbe
omer, רבי Rebbe used to say, מנין שבמידה שאדם מודד בה מודדין
לו. minayin sheb'midah she'adam moded bah modedin lo. How do you know
in the same measure that a person measures in this world, they
measure against... he's... that measure's meted out for him, you know, up
in, you know, through heaven, he gets appropriate payback. So do you
have a scriptural source for this? Yeah, well, let's take a look.
Okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, as it says, בסאסאה בשלחה תריבנה. b'se'ase'ah b'shalchah terivenah.
In its measure, in its in its sending in exile, you know,
it will be it will be smitten or it'll be like a
attack against it. So that is in its measure. They're going to
be punished in its measure. אין לי אלא סאה. Ein li ela
se'ah. Now it's also a little play that a סאה se'ah is
a very specific type of a measure, it's a large measure. So
maybe if somebody does a big sin, that's worthy of God getting
involved, of being a divinely ordained punishment, of it being מידה כנגד
מידה, middah kineged middah, but מנין לרבות תרקב וחצי תרקב קב וחצי
קב רובע וחצי רובע טומן וכולה? minayin lerabos tirkah v'chatzi tirkah kav
v'chatzi kav rovah v'chatzi rovah tuman v'uchulei? How do you know even
these tiny little measures? How do you know even if it's a
gram, right? It's not a gallon. It's how do you know how,
you know, about an ounce, a quart, a gram, I'm switching measurement
systems anyway. So how do you know a teaspoon? How do you
know even a teaspoon is measured out against somebody? מנין? minayin? תלמוד
לומר כי... Talmud lomar ki... סואן ברעש. soen barash.
Now,
I don't know, I looked at the English of this, it was
something like every shoe is somehow, I don't know, whatever the English
is. But here, every measure is... Right. Right, so it's, so it's
translated, I'm just saying the פשט pshat of סאון seon at least
whatever the translations I looked at last night is not measure, but
it's reading סאון seon as סאה. seah. So every measure, every measure
a person does is measured out against them. Okay. ומניין שכל פרוטה
ופרוטה מצטרפת לחשבון גדול. Uminayin shekol pruta upruta mitztarefet lecheshbon gadol. Now
how do you know that every tiny little thing adds up to
a big thing? Which maybe means that sometimes, you know, on the
one hand, you will be punished for every little thing, and maybe
actually you'll get a little punishment for a little thing, but maybe
sometimes you won't get a little punishment for a little thing, you
know, but it'll all... yeah,
exactly, will wait to sort of collect all of the little things,
and then you'll get punished for, you'll get punished for the totality.
So how do you know that that happens? תלמוד לומר אחת לאחת
למצוא חשבון, Talmud lomar achat leachat limtzo cheshbon, one to one to
finally get a significant number. וכן מצינו בסוטה, Vechen matzinu besotah,
and we similarly found by a סוטה. sotah. That was just קהלת,
Kohelet, like thinking about this, like oh yeah, like you know, I
added it all together and this is what I came up with.
Right. It's a free use of פסוקים pesukim to make the argument.
Okay.
וכן מצינו בסוטה שבמידה שמדדה בה מדדו לה. Vechen matzinu besotah shebemidah
shemadadah bah madedu lah.
In the way that she was measured it was measured out against
her. By the way, it is interesting, you know, just the language
of the plural here, מדדו לה. madedu lah. מידה שהאדם מודד מודדין,
Midah shehaadam moded modedin,
right? So it's like the heavenly court, you know, they, right, no,
because it's clear it's all, well that's the interesting thing I'm saying
here. Here you actually have people doing half of God's work. But
normally, right, when it's, you know, instead of saying like a guy
falls off a roof or falls in a fire, whatever, so it's
interesting sort of the use of the plural, you know, נעשה אדם,
naaseh adam, like, you know, whatever. Okay. The heavenly court. Anyway, שבמידה
שמדדה, shebemidah shemadadah, thank you, מדדו לה. madedu lah. היא עמדה על
פתח ביתה לראות לו. Hi amdah al petach beitah leraot lo.
She stood by the doorway of her house to be visible to
this man, to seduce him or whatever or to be waiting for
him when he showed up.
ולפיכך כהן kohen מעמידה על שער ניקנור ומראה קלונה לכל. maamidah al
shaar nikanor umareh klonah lakol.
Makes a public spectacle of her, demonstrates her embarrassment, her shaming to
everyone. Again, the presumption of guilt. היא פרסה לו סודרים נאים על
ראשה. Hi parsah lo sudarin naim al roshah.
She presumably put silks and beautiful things on her head. ולפיכך כהן
kohen נוטל כיפה מעל ראשה ומניחה תחת רגליה. notel kipah meal roshah
umenichah tachat ragleiha. And therefore her cap is removed from her head
and her hair is disheveled. היא כחלה לו פניה. Hi kachalah lo
paneiha. She made up her face. ולפיכך פניה, דף ט' עמוד א',
daf tet amud alef, פניה מוריקות. paneiha morikot. Therefore now we're getting
not to the כהן kohen but what happens when she drinks the
water, her, her face will like literally become a jaundice, like, you
know. So, היא כחלה לו עיניה. Hi kachalah lo eineiha.
She presumably made up, put makeup on her eyes. ולפיכך עיניה בולטות.
Ulefikach eineiha boltat. Her eyes will like bug out, a, you know,
what's it, bug out is the technical... bulge out,
thank you. Okay, right. Bugging out is something else. Bulge out, thank
you. היא קלעה לו את שערה. Hi kelaah lo et searah. She,
you know, sort of braided her hair, made her hair nice. ולפיכך
כהן kohen סותר את שערה. soter et searah. It's not just removing
the hair covering but it's disheveling the hair. If the hair is
braided, unbraiding it and so on. היא הראתה לו באצבע. Hi heratah
lo beetzba. She like, you know, summoned her, right, like what's the
word, beckoned him with her finger. ולפיכך ציפורניה נושרות. Ulefikach tziporneiha noshrot.
Her fingernails will drop out. We, that's the first we're hearing of
that. Okay. I guess that's what the משנה mishnah means of שאר
כל הגוף לא פלט. shear kol haguf lo palat. היא חגרה לו
בצלצול. Hi chagraah lo betziltzul. She wore a nice, a nice like
a belt. ולפיכך כהן kohen מביא חבל מצרי וקושר לה למעלה מדדיה.
mevi chevel mitzri vekosher lah lemalah midadieiha. Therefore the כהן kohen brings
this, you know, this Egyptian rope whatever that is and binds it
above her breasts to hold her garment up, but it's really like
an ugly type of a, of a cord. היא פשטה לו את
ירכה. Hi pashtah lo et yerechah.
She opened up her thighs for him. ולפיכך ירכה נופלת. Ulefikach yerechah
nofelet. Therefore her thighs fall, collapse. היא קבלתו על כרסה. Hi kiblatu
al kersah. So this is the ירך yerech and the בטן. beten.
She received him on her stomach. So again that just might mean
physically, right, you know, he's on top of her, supporting his weight
or something. Might also refer to the actual act of penetration depending,
right, depending on whether it's describing what it's referring to and it
says stomach here. ולפיכך בטנה צבה. Ulefikach bitnah tzavah. Therefore right, her
stomach blows up. And that is, it's going on the inside and
it's blowing up from the inside, so probably is more talking about
the penetration. היא האכילתו מעדני עולם. Hi hechilat’hu maadanei olam.
She fed him all of the delicacies of the world. Or it
could be the other way around, like maybe he enticed her. I
get, right, so thank you very much for pointing that out too,
which we, which is exactly that. It's something we pointed out before,
but it really needs to be reiterated here. Right? That it's besides
the fact that she is the only like she's the only one
being suspect and what about the
adulterer? The male adulterer. And probably part of that issue is like,
again, in a patriarchal society, a wife suspects her husband of committing
adultery, right, you know. what type of power does she have, you
know, in order to do anything with that accusation? And anyway, besides
which, let's also remember that the act of adultery, if a man
commits adultery against his wife, halakhically it's only adultery if he sleeps
with a married woman. It's not a betrayal of his wife because
in הלכה, halacha, you know, because from this perspective, I mean, obviously
חרם דרבינו גרשום Cherem de-Rabbeinu Gershom whatever, we've had a few thousand
years of development, but from that perspective, right, in a polygamous society,
sleeping with another woman isn't a betrayal of your wife, but sleeping
with a married woman is doing something to that married man. You
know, that's sort of like the problem there, right? Which explains the
whole dynamics about ultimately the married man is the injured party, right?
So that's why he's the one taking his wife, there's nobody to
really take the man. I mean, I guess the guy whose wife
it was, but again, he doesn't have power over her. So that's
just explaining why that dynamics, but Michael is one hundred percent correct,
no matter how you sort of conceive of who's the injured party,
it doesn't mean who is the initiator, who was the seducer, who
was the one that was at fault. So you're absolutely correct that
that again needs to be underscored, that she is sort of all
of the blame is being dumped on her because the whole ritual
is being done with her and not with the man. Yes, there's
some point that that's lingering down somewhere else as well where I'm
sorry, one more time, which language? Language like of oh well, she
dressed up, she you know like there's that an issue that anyone
who's been raped or assaulted or whatever, they were asking for it,
you know she why did she look like that if she didn't
want to be right? But yeah, that's also an excellent point, that
whole point about like right, because you know again it's like well
in a certain way, what do you expect from the man? If
she was doing this, the man is not can't do anything against
a woman's seductions and she's looking this way and it even removes
agency from the man that might be involved. Right, exactly. Also very
kind of simplistic. I mean the גמרא Gimara imagines this whole almost
romantic encounter which is not necessarily the right,
right? Well I don't know if it's romantic, it's seduction, but yeah
but yeah right, could be a lot of other reasons, sexual money,
right, a lot of other reasons, exactly. Okay,
look you know, all you gotta do is read a little bit
of משלי Mishlei and you know which so many things at the
beginning are about the seductive woman and it's used there as a
metaphor but it's only a metaphor because it's a powerful image, right,
you know? So anyway, so okay, but yeah it's that definitely what
needs to be pointed out and reiterated. Interesting here by the way
also is doubling back, right? It talks about the water impacting her,
right, and then it sort of goes to the קרבן, korban, right?
So it sort of like and the קרבן korban actually comes before
the water, the water comes at the end of the whole process.
Okay, so anyway, היא האכילה אותו מעדני עולם, hi heechila oto maadanei
olam, she made him drink all of these delicacies or made him
eat or she fed him, לפיכך קרבנה מאכל בהמה, lefichach korbanah maachal
behemah,
her קרבן korban is the you know made out of שעורים, seorim,
out of barley, like animal food. היא השקתה אותו יין משובח בכוסות
משובחין, hi hishkata oto yayin meshubach bekosot meshubachin, she made him drink
or didn't make him drink she gave him
drink thank you, you know,
high quality wine in beautiful goblets, לפיכך כהן משקה מים המרים בקדא
של חרס, lefichach kohen mashke mayim hamarim bekeda shel cheres,
therefore the כהן kohen makes her drink bitter water in this like
pottery you know cup. היא עשתה בסתר, hi asta baseter,
she did her deeds in private and in hiding so nobody else
should know except when she was standing on the door and beckoning
him, but okay. יושב בסתר עליון שם פנים, yoshev beseter elyon sam
panim,
the one who dwells on high in seclusion up high, he will
he will you know pay attention to her. רש״י Rashi says שם
פנים sam panim is like to punish her but also שם פנים
sam panim is like you know פנים panim means like give a
face to her, make it public, make it public, שנאמר sheneemar ועין
נואף שמרה נשף, ve-ein noef shamra neshef,
the eye of the adulterer like keeps in the darkness, לאמר לא
תשורני עין, lemor lo teshureni ayin, nobody will see me. So she
thinks she's gonna get away with it and it's all gonna be
done in private, God is gonna publicize the sin. דבר אחר, davar
acher, היא עשתה בסתר, hi asta baseter, so actually maybe a little
bit I was already reading the next line because the next line
is emphasizing the publicize. היא עשתה בסתר, hi asta baseter, she did
it in private, המקום פרסמה בגלוי, Hamakom pirsemah bagalui, God publicized it
in in public, שנאמר sheneemar תכסה שנאה במשאון תגלה רעתו בקהל, techaseh
sinah bemashaon tigaleh raato bekahal,
the one who hides up the I don't know what the hatred
but רש״י Rashi says it's a hated deed in the darkness, the
evil will be revealed in in the community. So that's why we're
doing this public spectacle and again making it all about an assumption
of guilt and a punishment. So that's why רש״י Rashi said the
previous one of שם פנים sam panim just means focus His attention
on her and here we're emphasizing the public nature. Okay, so that's
all of the מידה כנגד מידה. middah kneged middah. ומאחר דנפקא ליה
מאחת לאחת, ume'achar denafka leh meachas lachas,
once we learn now the גמרא Gimara takes over from the ברייתא.
Braita. Once we learn out from one for one that, you know,
that we add up every little, we add up, little things get
added up for a big punishment. So למצוא חשבון, limtzo cheshbon, כי
כל סאון סואן ברעש למה לי? ki kol seon soen bera'ash lama
li? Why do you need, what does it tell me for every
measure if we're already telling every little thing gets kept? No, למידה.
lemidah. It's not just telling you that every little thing gets kept,
that you get אחת לאחת למצוא חשבון, achat le'achat limtzo cheshbon, every
little misdeed you're going to be punished for. It's telling you that
the punishment is measure for measure and even sometimes a little punishment
for a little thing, but everything will be measure for measure. מאחר
דנפקא ליה me'achar denafqa leh from כי כל סאון סואן ברעש, ki
kol seon soen bera'ash, once we learn out from every measure, even
a small measure, בסאסאה בשלחה תריבנה למה לי? besasa'ah beshalchah terivena lama
li? Why does it have to say in the fill of its
measure, you know, when it's being driven out I will punish it?
So that we said was a סאה, se'ah, big measure. So what's
the point of that? וכדרבי חנינא בר פפא. ukiderabi chanina bar papa.
You're right, that's to tell you something else, not מדה כנגד מדה,
midah keneged midah, another thing, like רבי חנינא בר פפא. Rabi Chanina
bar Papa. דאמר רבי חנינא בר פפא אין הקדוש ברוך הוא נפרע
מן האומה עד שעת שילוחה. de'amar Rabi Chanina bar Papa en Hakadosh
Baruch Hu nifra min ha'umah ad she'at shiluchah.
God will only punish a nation, you know, at the time when
it is being driven out or sent into exile. Now רש"י Rashi
says here and it seems from the גמרא Gemara it doesn't only
mean sent into exile, but being destroyed. So like all the punishment
is held up, it's held back until the ultimate moment of destruction.
So נאמר בסאסאה בשלחה תריבנה. ne'emar besasa'ah beshalchah terivena.
So the measurement will be measured out. So maybe for an individual,
you know, at different times in a person's life, you will have
the מדה כנגד מדה, midah keneged midah, but at a national level,
you know, a nation could be, I mean, also, look, part of
the problem with all of this is the opening סוגיא sugya in
ברכות. Berachot. You know, how do you deal with צדיק ורע לו
רשע וטוב לו? tzadik vera lo rasha vetov lo? You have a
very nice idea about שכר ועונש, sachar va'onesh, right, every מדה כנגד
מדה. midah keneged midah. It doesn't always seem to work out that
way, right? So the גמרא Gemara is not raising that question here,
it's just asserting the מדה כנגד מדה. midah keneged midah. We'll worry
about if it doesn't work out that way, you know, at some
other time. But here what it is also dealing with is, you
know, particularly an issue like what it must look like. You know,
here is רומי, Romi, this oppressive nation, right, you know, here are
all these other nations that not only are not Jewish, but have
done a lot of evil to the Jews, and they're, all they
are is successful, right? Where is the divine justice in that? You
know, how come they, you know, they continue to flourish? So no,
no, all their punishment is being held back to the final יום
הדין, yom hadin, to the day when ultimately God is going to
bring all their punishment upon them. So that's the emphasis here by
an אומה. umah. Okay, so let's just read a little bit more.
What? It does send prophets all the time to try and prevent
that. Yeah, but the actual punishment that they deserve, like a nation
could be successful like רומי Romi for how many hundreds of years,
right? So, okay, let's just read a little bit more about this.
It
says איני? eni? והאמר רבא שלש כוסות האמורות במצרים למה לי? veha'amar
Rava shalosh kosot ha'amorot bemitzrayim lama li? When it says by יוסף
Yosef by the dream, the three cups, you know, that was being
the שר המשקים, sar hamashkim, the wine steward, you know, וכוס פרעה
בידי וכוס פרעה vekhos Paroh beyadi vekhos Paroh etc. it says כוס
פרעה khos Paroh three times. Why? So this is a metaphor of
like to have them drink from the dregs, you know, drinking from
the wine, the poison of the punishment, you know, the poisonous wine.
So that's, that's they're going to get their punishment. So why does
it say that three times?
אחת ששתה בימי משה, achat sheshata bimei Moshe, one measure of their
punishment they got at the time of משה, Moshe, you know, קריאת
ים סוף Kriat Yam Suf and the plagues, etc., ואחת ששתה בימי
פרעה נכה ve'achat sheshata bimei Paroh Necho at the time of פרעה
נכה, Paroh Necho, which was by נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, he went there and
when he was, you know, doing all of his other world conquering,
he conquered מצרים, Mitzrayim, ואחת שעתידה לשתות עם חברותיה ve'achat she'atida lishtot
im chaveroteha and the one that they'll get with all the other
nations in the, you know, in the times of משיח. Mashiach. So
here you see a nation is being punished in spread out, not
all at once. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא הנהו
אזלו והני אחריני נינהו? vechi tema hanhu azlu vehani achrini ninhu? Ah,
wait, maybe the people now living in מצרים Mitzrayim are not the
Egyptians of the time of משה. Moshe. You know, it's actually interesting,
right, that some people, you know, don't refuse to translate, you know,
in an English translation by מצרים Mitzrayim like Egypt or Egyptians,
you know, because you identify it with the people that are there
right now, and it's not the same nation. You're going to repeat,
so right, so maybe you'll say no, the מצרים Mitzrim of משה,
Moshe, they were wiped out, they got their full punishment or whatever.
They're, you know, this is, so then it's funny though, but then
even if it is אחריני, achrini, the idea oh, they'll get שלוש
כוסות shalosh kosot spread out over time, if it's אחריני, achrini, then
it's not שלוש כוסות shalosh kosot spread out of time, it's three
different nations getting three different punishments. But anyway, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Anyway, you can't say that, דתניא אמר רבי יהודה מנימין
גר מצרי. detanya amar Rabi Yehuda Manimin ger Mitzri. היה לי חבר
מתלמידי רבי עקיבא. haya li chaver mitalmidei Rabi Akiva. רבי יהודה Rabi
Yehuda taught, I had a, I had a colleague from the students
of רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva who was a, a convert, a מצרי
Mitzri convert. His name was מנימין. Manimin. ואמר מנימין ve'amar Manimin and
this מנימין Manimin said to me, גר מצרי ראשון אני, ger Mitzri
rishon ani, I am a first generation מצרי Mitzri convert. ונשאתי מצרית
ראשונה venasati Mitzrit rishona and I married a first generation מצרית Mitzrit
convert.
אשיא לבני מצרית שניה, ashia livni Mitzrit sheniya, I will have my
son marry a second generation מצרית Mitzrit convert, okay, so who both
of her parents, the כלה's kalah parents and the חתן's chatan parents
are all first generation converts, and so the kids are second generation
converts and they'll marry one another.
כדי שבן בני, kedei sheben beni, so my grand— so my grandkids
will be מותר לבוא בקהל, mutar lavo bekahal, will be permissible to
marry naturally born Jews, דור שלישי יבא בקהל ה', dor shlishi yavo
bekahal Hashem, because the הלכה halacha is basically בייחוסים הולך אחר הפסול
beyuchsin holech achar hapsul that if the parents are of different levels
of— one is כשר, kosher, one is פסול, pasul, you know one
has some type of a פסול, psul, a ממזר, mamzer, מצרי, Mitzri,
whatever, or a first generation מצרי, Mitzri, second generation, you always follow
the parent that has
the greater disqualification— that’s not the word but anyway,
that has
the greater disqualification. So therefore you only have a second generation מצרי
Mitzri if both parents are first generation, and you only have a
third generation if both parents are second. Okay, so that’s why it
says and then that’s how we’ll arrange it so the third generation
will be able to marry natural born Jews. So the point is
here we are in the time of the תנאים Tannaim and we’re
assuming we’re still dealing with מצרים Mitzrim from the time of the
תורה, Torah, so you see it is the same nation. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela ee itmar
hachi itmar, but fine, it’s not true. Nations, it’s not that all
the punishment gets stored up for the end. Here’s how the statement
was said. אמר רבי חיננא בר פפא אין הקדוש ברוך הוא נפרע
מן המלך עד ששלחה. amar Rabbi Chinana bar Pappa ein Hakadosh Baruch
Hu nifra min hamelech ad sheshlucha. A king will only be punished
when he is ultimately presumably like
dethroned, שנאמר בסאסאה בשלחה תריבנה, shene’emar besasa beshalcha trivenna, talking not about
the nation but about the punishment coming on the king. אממימר מתני
להא דרבי חיננא בר פפא הא. Amemar matni lehada deRabbi Chinana bar
Pappa aha. אממימר Amemar taught this teaching of רבי חיננא בר פפא
Rabbi Chinana bar Pappa about the nation, not the king, but he
taught it on the following verse. מאי דכתיב, mai dichtsiv, what’s meant
by the verse כי אני ה' לא שניתי ואתם בני יעקב לא
כליתם, ki ani Hashem lo shanisi v’atem benei Yaakov lo chilitem, I
God have not changed and you the children of Jacob have not
been destroyed. אני ה' לא שניתי, ani Hashem lo shanisi, לא שניתי
לאומה ושניתי לה, lo shanisi le’uma v’shanisi lah, I never smote a
nation twice. If I’m going to smite a nation, I’m going to
wipe them out, okay? So that’s in general. ואתם בני יעקב, v’atem
benei Yaakov, but when it comes to you, בני ישראל, Benei Yisrael,
לא כליתם, lo chilitem, you were smitten and you were not destroyed.
You have not yet been— you have not ceased. היינו דכתיב hainu
dichtsiv and that’s like the פסוק pasuk that
says וחצי אכלה בם, v’chitzai achaleh bam, חצי כלין והן אינם כלין,
chitzai kalin v’hein einam kalin, my arrows will be emptied out but
they will still survive. So even after we have suffered all of
this from the nations and even here from God, nevertheless we still
survive. Other nations, if God is going to attack them they’ll be
wiped out, so the גמרא Gemara there doesn’t then ask the question
that just asked before, which is but it didn’t happen because by
the מצרים Mitzrim it was over time. All right, anyway but here
it’s another פסוק, pasuk, it’s focusing in a different way and it
isn’t making the same assertion that we had rejected a minute ago
that it is— that it is a full punishment all at once
for other nations. By the way, a long תוספות Tosafot here and
even רש"י Rashi discusses the idea
that in the תוספתא, Tosefta, which this is quoting from where רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda quotes— says that I’m a second generation etc., רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says to him מנים פאיתא, manim paita,
you’re making a mistake, you’re not the original מצרים Mitzrim in the
תורה, Torah, סנחריב ובלבל את האומות, Sancheriv ubilbel es ha’umos,
the people living in מצרים Mitzrayim now are not the people that
were the מצרים Mitzrim of the time of the תורה. Torah. So
it’s interesting that here the גמרא Gemara sort of accepts the testimony
and elsewhere we actually do reject it and do say that it’s
not the same that’s being referred to in the תורה. Torah. Yes.
Oh, Rabbi Edov had a question first a while ago, yes. So
with all this measure for measure thing, have we discussed yet whether
in the סוטה— Sotah what was her fate? Does she die from
the— no, that’s coming up. We’re sort of presuming it although we
haven’t said it yet, but that’s coming up. We have not said
it, that’s a later משנה. Mishnah. Now this Dov, we’re going in
order. Yes. What’s the difference between אי איתמר הכי איתמר ee itmar
hachi itmar and חסורי מחסרא הכי קתני? chisuri michsra hachi kasani? Oh,
because here we’re not changing the text, we’re saying—
oh yeah, you’re right, we are changing the text.
I think חסורי מחסרא chisuri michsra is by a תנאי Tannaic source,
this is an אמוראי Amoraic source. Yes, אמר רבי חיננא בר פפא?
amar Rabbi Chinana bar Pappa? Yeah, even though it’s great Hebrew. Yeah,
well the late members of the אמוראים Amoraim are in Hebrew. It’s
only the סתם stam of the גמרא Gemara that’s in Aramaic. Gotcha.
Yeah.
I can’t believe you have maintained this argument. סוטה’s Sotah punishment מידה
כנגד מידה, mida keneged mida, we looked at the פסוקים pesukim that
are the basis of מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida in general,
and one of those פסוקים pesukim was בסאסאה בשלחה תריבנה. besasa beshalcha
trivenna. We said that that פסוק pasuk seemed a little redundant because
we learned out the principle of מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida
from other פסוקים. pesukim. So he’s saying, okay fine, that teaches you
a different principle: that God when God will— God only punishes a
king or a nation, he brings it all at the end. That
doesn’t relate back. That’s just some tying up loose ends. Okay, and
about today about Egyptians in the three generations. Yeah, they’re not the
same. Yeah, they can’t marry, right. Yep. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Now we get back though to the main theme of מידה כנגד
מידה. mida keneged mida. אמר amar, רבי המנונא *Amar Rabbi Chamnuna*: אין
הקדוש ברוך הוא נפרע מן האדם עד שתמלא סאתו *Ein HaKadosh Baruch
Hu nifrah min ha'adam ad shetimale se'ato*. Now, now though, we are
taking this idea of what was said by in a nation, applying
it to a person because again, every time the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
makes these bold assertions about everybody gets proper judgment in this world,
שכר ועונש *schar v'onesh*, there has to be a little bit of
a recognition that things don't work out that simply. So here the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is actually saying you know what? Even for people
really, not just for nations, you know, they don't get punished until
their full- until their measure is full. And the metaphor of measure
works here, right? So it's ironic. Before we said even a little
measure, like even a thimble you're going to get paid back. But
now we're shifting. No, no, no. There's a big measure. Everything is
going into that, you know, into that big- into that big box.
And until that box is full, it's not yet time for punishment.
So that explains how people can be successful who deserve- who sin
and are רשעים *resha'im* and so on. Their measure isn't full. Okay,
so now we're assuming only a big measure essentially. Different than what
we were assuming before. Does תשובה *teshuva* mitigate? What? תשובה *teshuva* always
mitigates. But like we're- again, the implicit thing here is to deal
with- you know, implicitly the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* hasn't said explicitly, things
don't work out this neatly, right? People are punished measure for measure.
So one way is, don't worry, eventually he'll get his comeuppance, you
know. So yeah. Amazon shipping algorithms as a metaphor for sin and
punishment. He'll ship- ship everything at once.
Okay,
except you don't want to be a Prime, you don't want to
be Amazon Prime because then you get everything right away. Or anyway,
maybe that's better, you don't get a big punishment at the end.
הקדוש ברוך הוא *HaKadosh Baruch Hu*. Yeah, exactly. All right. All right.
Got a whole דרשה *drasha* right there, yes. Does the- the way
it's presented with the סוטה *Sotah* the possibility that they're- they're prefacing
the whole thing by saying this is a woman with a track
record? No. Where do you see that? Well you get the whole
idea of accumulating issues and accumulating- and it's not- there's not really
a punishment brought forth until there- you reach a certain critical mass
that brings- I don't think- I mean you can see if you
see an echo of that. I don't see it circling back to
סוטה *Sotah* in that regard. You know, maybe it's a way of
dealing with why are we presuming guilt? So maybe there- maybe you're
right. Maybe this isn't taken frivolously, it's a woman that really has
a track record. Well her whole track record is the קינוי וסתירה
*kinui v'stira*, but- a certain critical mass that brings- maybe. That's interesting.
I hadn't thought about that. My sense is it's more dealing with
like צדיק tzaddik ורע לו *tzaddik v'ra lo*, right? But maybe- exactly.
Okay, so let's take a look. Okay. אמר רבי המנונא: אין הקדוש
ברוך הוא נפרע מן האדם עד שתמלא סאתו *Amar Rabbi Chamnuna: ein
HaKadosh Baruch Hu nifrah min ha'adam ad shetimale se'ato*, until his measure
is filled. And again now we're to a סאה *se'ah*, it's a
big measure, right? It's not a מידה midah. *middah*. Until the big
measure is full. שנאמר: Sheneemar, במלאות ספקו יצר לו *Shene'emar: bimlot sifko
yetzer lo*. By when his- only when his like- his like- his
desires are satisfied, then it will be- he will be anguished for
him, troubled for him, then will he be punished. דרש רבי חנינא
בר פפא *Darash Rabbi Chanina bar Papa*: מה דכתיב *mai d'ichtiv*, what's
meant by the verse, רננו צדיקים בה' לישרים נאוה תהלה *Ranenu tzaddikim
ba'Hashem laysharim nava tehila*, right, rejoice צדיקים *tzaddikim* in God. So this
is the only reason we're quoting this now, Jenna, just so you
know, complete digression but it's the same person, רבי חנינא בר פפא
*Rabbi Chanina bar Papa*. So there's not even going to be necessarily
a thematic connection here, okay? What is meant by that verse? So
to the righteous is- is attractive praise. אל תקרי נאוה תהלה אלא
נוה תהלה *Al tikrei nava tehila ela naveh tehila*, the domicile. זה
משה Moshe ודוד שלא שלטו שונאיהם במעשיהם *Zeh Moshe v'David shelo shaltu
soneihem bema'aseihem*. This is משה Moshe, *Moshe* and דוד David *David* that
their נוה *naveh*, the- the domicile that they created for God, the
dwelling place was never- the enemies never benefited from it. דוד דכתיב:
טבעו בארץ שעריה *David d'ichtiv: tave'u va'aretz she'areha*, so quoting a פסוק
*pasuk* from איכה *Eicha*, right, which is a bad thing, but it
says that the gates sort of sank into the ground. But the
point was, no, no, no. The gates of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* were out of gold or out of, you know,
precious work and before the enemies could capture it, they- they sank
into the ground. משה Moshe, דאמר מר: משנבנה מקדש ראשון נגנז אהל
מועד קרשיו קרסיו ובריחיו ועמודיו ואדניו *Moshe d'amar mar: mishenivna mikdash rishon
nignaz ohel moed krashav krasav uvrichav ve'amudav va'adanav*. When the first בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* was built, what happened to all of
the hooks and the beams and the- and the, you know, and
the- the cloths or whatever? That was all buried, secreted away. So
ultimately the meaning being it wouldn't be captured when the בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash* was destroyed. I don't know if that was the intent,
but that's the point. And therefore it was never captured. היכא *Heicha*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, so where are they hidden?
So אמר רב חסדא אמר אבימי *Amar Rav Chisda amar Avimi*: תחת
מחילות של היכל *Tachat mechilot shel heichal*, underneath the tunnels that run
underneath the היכל *heichal* in הר הבית *Har HaBayit* where the- where
the basic, you know, קודש *kodesh* was built. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan.
סוטה *Tanu rabanan: Sotah*, back to סוטה *Sotah*. נתנה עיניה במי שאינו
ראוי ra'uy. לה *Natna eineha bemi she'eino ra'uy lah*, she- put her
eyes, she desired something that was not- she was not fit for
her, somebody who wasn't her husband. מה שביקשה לא ניתן לה ומה
שבידה נטלו הימנה *Mah shebiksha lo nittan lah u'mah shebeyada natlu heimena*.
What she wanted she doesn't get,
and what she had, her marriage, her relationship with her husband, that
was taken away. So here's like a different message, not just you'll
get punished and מידה כנגד מידה mida keneged mida, *middah k'neged middah*
and divine justice and so on, but the message is like, be
happy with what you have. Like, you know, you're always desiring... or
more and ultimately it's going to just lead
to you losing all of the good things that you have with
you right now. שכל הנותן עיניו במה שאינו שלו,
anybody who gives his eyes and lusts after something that is not
theirs and, you know, is not a fitting thing to be desiring,
מה שמבקש אין נותנין לו, ma she'mevakesh ein notnin lo, he doesn't
get what he's desiring, ומה שבידו נוטלין הימנו, u'ma she'beyado notlin heimenu,
and what he does have he winds up losing. Okay, that doesn't
always work either, but okay, but often actually there's probably more real
life experience of this than there is of the מידה כנגד מידה,
midah keneged midah. you know, that people like, you know, if you
would just sort of been happy with what you had and then
people like, you know, especially now whatever, you know, I mean a
major part of the whole advertising industry is to make us desire
things that we never knew we desired before we started watching the
ads or whatever, you know, to whet that desire. And then does
it make us any happier? Anyway, וכן מצינו בנחש הקדמוני. ve'chen matzinu
be'nachash ha'kadmoni. And then we found by the original serpent שנתן עיניו
במה שאינו ראוי לו. she'natan einav be'ma she'eino ra'uy lo. He gave
his eyes, this is again dealing with sexual desire, the
understanding of חז"ל chazal that he desired, you know, to have sex
with חוה, Chava, he desired something that was not fit for him.
I mean, not only was she married, she was a human. מה
שביקש לא ניתן לו. ma she'bikesh lo nitan lo. Thank you for
that illuminating detail. Sure. What he desired wasn't given to him. ומה
שבידו נטלו ממנו u'ma she'beyado natlu mimenu and what he had was
taken from him because apparently if he was cursed that he was
going to go on his on his stomach, presumably beforehand he was
walking upright. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar ha'kadosh baruch hu, God said,
אני אמרתי יהיה מלך על כל הבהמה, ani amarti yihiye melech al
kol ha'behema,
I wanted him to be the king, הוא ערום מכל, hu arum
mi'kol, ועכשיו ארור הוא מכל הבהמה מכל חיית השדה. ve'achshav arur hu
mi'kol ha'behema mi'kol chayat ha'sadeh.
Now he's at the bottom of the animal kingdom. אני אמרתי יהלך
בקומה זקופה, ani amarti yelech be'koma zkufa, he would go upright. עכשיו
על גחונך תלך, achshav al gechoncha telech,
he goes on his on his stomach. אני אמרתי יהיה מאכלו מאכל
אדם, ani amarti yihiye ma'achalo ma'achal adam, he would eat from the
from the, you know, human food. עכשיו עפר יאכל, achshav afar yochal,
now he eats dust. הוא אמר אהרוג את האדם ואשא את חוה.
hu amar ehrog et ha'adam ve'esa et Chava. He said I want
to get אדם Adam killed, I'll have through חוה Chava I'll get
אדם Adam to sin, and then I'll be able to marry חוה.
Chava. עכשיו איבה אשית בינך ובין האישה. achshav eiva ashit beinecha u'vein
ha'isha.
Instead of having you have a sexual relationship with חוה, Chava, now
there'll be hatred between you and the woman ובין זרעך ובין זרעה.
u'vein zar'acha u'vein zar'ah. וכן מצינו בקין ובקורח ובלעם ודואג ואחיתופל וגיחזי
ואבשלום ואדוניהו ויואב והמן. ve'chen matzinu be'kayin u've'korach u'vileam ve'doeg ve'achitofel ve'geichazi
ve'avshalom ve'adoniyahu ve'yoav ve'haman. Okay,
you can go ahead and unpack that whole list. Okay, but a
lot of the same people here clearly are people that, you know,
lusted and desired for things, they weren't happy with what they had.
Interesting for קין, Kayin, רש"י Rashi says it means הבל's Hevel's twin
sister, you know, like there's some פשט peshat that like all קין
Kayin and הבל Hevel were born with twin sisters, so he desired,
you know, he desired the sister that wasn't his, I guess not
הבל's Hevel's twin sister, that was presumably the one he married. But
okay, maybe his own sister. Anyway, רש"י Rashi makes it sexual, which
is interesting because he could just say, you know, the מדרש Midrash
sort of says what were קין Kayin and הבל Hevel fighting about?
A fascinating מדרש. Midrash. It says one said, you know, in my
חלק chelek will be the בית המקדש, the other said in my
חלק chelek will be the בית המקדש. The other says I have
the whole world, the other says I have the whole world. It's
a very great מדרש Midrash because it talks about like what is
it that get people to, you know, what leads to so passionate,
like religion, you know, wealth, I forgot what the third one was.
Anyway, whatever קין Kayin was fighting about he wanted the other half
of the world that he couldn't have because of הבל. Hevel. Anyway,
but you have everybody else here right, like קורח Korach obviously he
wanted the כהונה, kehuna, בלעם Bilam presumably he wanted wealth, go through
the whole list. Anyway, אבשלום Avshalom wanted the מלכות malchut etc. etc.
מה שנתנו עיניהם במה שאינו ראוי להם, ma she'natnu eineihem be'ma she'eino
ra'uy lahem, they desired something that not only they didn't have. You
know, like it's interesting, they're not saying you're not allowed to desire
something more, right? I mean what are you going to do, deny
the basic, you know, human sense of wanting something and desiring something?
But there's a sense of ראוי. ra'ui What does it mean that's
appropriate for you to want and desire? Either appropriate because it's like
it's a reasonable thing to desire, it's not a crazy like lust
out of proportion, and B, you know, it's also something that is
like permissible to you as opposed to a lot of these things
are things that are forbidden to you, you know. But anyway but
it's not saying you're not allowed to have any desire, that's not
what they're saying. מה שביקשו לא ניתן להם ומה שבידם נטלו מהם.
ma she'bikshu lo nitan lahem u'ma she'beyadam natlu meihem. So when you
really have these desires that are out of proportion, that are inappropriate
for various reasons,
then ultimately it'll just lead to, you know, lead to disappointment. Yes.
Even things like you might desire like an iPhone, but the examples
that they give are all people who have done more than just
covet their iPhone and they've actually acted on their desire. Right, that's
a good point. It's not just the desire, it's that the acting
on their desire. That's true. It's not you're right, you're right, just
having like
fantasizing and dreaming, it's like to it's right, it's pursuing that desire.
Of course it's also very funny because, you know, sometimes you have
these very inspiring stories, right, about somebody that has this crazy dream.
Like I was just listening I listened to The Moth this broadcast
and somebody just said, you know, when he was growing up he
dreamed that he was going to play together like jazz with I
forget who it was, like some crazy crazy dream. And then he
tells the story that eventually it actually came true, you know, because
then you set your eyes on that and you, you know, and
you and you do things in your life to actually make it
more and more possible to close that gap, right? So, but the
point I think would be well that would be ראוי להם, ra'ui
lahem, you know? There's a question of how do you define what's
ראוי ra'ui. and not ראוי. So, but it is sometimes funny, sometimes
the whole point is that we should, you know, have a dream
that we pursue. Yes, passion. It's the Midrashic idea that Cain and
Abel each had a twin sister and that each pair of siblings
would then procreate and populate. Yeah, yeah, but he wanted the other.
Right, exactly.
Yeah, that's what Rashi quotes. Yeah, I think it's crazy. Before the
fall, pride. Rashi says, Rashi says that there was two, right? I
just double-checked Rashi. Rashi says that there were, Rashi says that there
were two twin sisters, Abel had two twin sisters, he married one,
he wanted the other one. Of course I don't get it, because
who was the other twin sister supposed to marry? If Cain married
one, Abel married the other, and each one had two twin sisters,
what was going to happen to those other two girls? I don't
know, anyway. Yes, young women. I was thinking of the phrase before
the fall, pride. Yeah, pride, right, pride comes before the fall, right.
I mean, all these, it's like, right, there's also that sense of,
right, the אינו ראוי eino ra'ui is coming to us, that's a
good point, looking at what Hashem's plan. Right, that's a good point,
part of the אינו ראוי eino ra'ui is like that sense of
like, I want it, I deserve it, like, you know, and I'm
entitled. Right, right. Is that a phrase from?
Pride comes before the fall, it might be from the other, the
other religion. Okay, the other
religion. No, no, אותו הספר, oto hasefer, אותו הספר. oto hasefer. Okay.
No, I think it's...
It might be. You can look it up. Somebody will check their
iPhone. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Okay. בירך התחילה בעבירה, beyarech
hitchila ba'aveira,
she began with the thigh. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? So
how do you know, not describing what she did, how do you
know that the impact of the water first begins with the thigh
and then goes to the to the to the belly? תימא משום
דכתיב בתת ה' אותך לאלה ולשבועה בתת ה' את ירכך נופלת ואת
בטנך צבה, teima mishum dechtiv betet Hashem otach le'ala velishvua betet Hashem
et yerechech nofelet ve'et bitnech tzeva, that's the curse, God will give
your thigh to fall and your belly to bloat. והכתיב, vehatichtiv,
but the other verse says, וצבתה בטנה ונפלה ירכה, vetzavta bitnah venafela
yerechah, when the water goes in, it says the opposite order, her
belly will bloat and her thigh will fall. So, אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, so which is it? No, כי לייט לייט
ברישא ירך והדר בטן, ki layet layet bereisha yerech vehadar beten, when
it's cursed, first the Cohen curses the thigh and then the belly
because of the order of the sin, like we were saying. ומיא
בטן לייט, umaya beten layet,
and the water, כי בדקי כי אורחיהו בדקי, ki badkei ki orchaihu
badkei, when they do their work,
so they do it by the way it goes through the body,
first the belly and then thigh. First of all, it's interesting to
note the word בדקי, badkei, they are בודק, bodek, they are testing
her innocence or her guilt. So again, you know, side by side
of completely assuming her guilt, you know, where it's, this is like
a reverse, we're treating this water in its act of meeting out
the punishment, framing it as a clarifying her guilt, you know, so
the ritual rational and judicial. Right. So, בטן, beten, okay, כי אורחיהו
בדקי, ki orchaihu badkei, בטן ברישא והדר ירך. beten bereisha vehadar yerech.
Okay, so Gemara says, one minute, בכולא נמי כתיב, bechula nami ketiv,
but it also says even in the curse it says that order
of that you just described.
First to belly and then the thigh. לצבות בטן ולנפיל ירך, latzbot
beten velanpil yerech, to bloat the belly and to cause the thigh
to fall. So Gemara says no, ההוא דמודע לה כהן דבטן ברישא
והדר ירך. hahu demoda lah Kohen debeten bereisha vehadar yerech. No, no,
the Cohen is telling her, if you look at the psukim he
says, the waters will enter into you to blow up the belly
and to make the thigh fall. So the Cohen is going to
describe what the waters are going to do in the order that
the waters will do it. שלא להוציא לעז על מים המאררים, shelo
lehotzi la'az al mayim hamarerim, so people won't say, hey, you said
it was going to be the reverse order and it was this
order. So he's describing the order, but when he curses her, he
curses her first about the thigh. So Rashi says, okay,
דמידה כנגד מידה, demidah keneged midah, you know, seems to be first
the בטן beten and then the ירך, yerech, not the order of
the sin. So I guess no, the curse itself is part of
the מידה כנגד מידה. midah keneged midah. The fact that the thigh
was cursed even before the waters had the effect, that was the
first punishment of the thigh, that was the מידה כנגד מידה. midah
keneged midah. What? It is
Mishlei? Okay. All right. So there we go. So David nailed it.
Okay, so שמשון, Shimshon, now we can do מידה כנגד מידה. midah
keneged midah. Our משנה, Mishna, like you have a, I mean look,
you know, you know how sometimes in נדרים Nedarim and נזיר Nazir
you have like two lines on a דף daf or something, this
is payback, this is our מידה. Anyway, but you know, it's fascinating
that the משנה Mishna itself is like a long elaborate אגדתא. Aggadeta.
Okay, so this משנה Mishna continues the מידה כנגד מידה. midah keneged
midah Let's take a look. Okay. שמשון הלך אחר עיניו, Shimshon halach
achar einav, Shimshon followed his eyes, also following that theme about going
after the things that you lust and is inappropriate, but it's within
the מידה כנגד מידה context. לפיכך נקרו פלשתים את עיניו, lefikach nikru
Plishtim et einav,
the Philistines poked out his eyes. שנאמר ויאחזו פלשתים וינקרו את עיניו,
shene'emar vayochezu Plishtim vayenakeru et einav, they seized him and they pierced
his eyes. אבשלום נתגאה בשערו, Avshalom nitga'eh bise'aro, Avshalom was haughty with
his hair. לפיכך נתלה בשערו, lefikach nitla bise'aro, therefore when he was
running away, the tree caught him in his hair and he was
captured and killed. ולפי שבא על עשר פילגשי אביו, ulefi sheba al
eser pilagshei aviv, because he had sex with his ten of his
father's concubines, לפיכך נתנו בו עשר לונביות, lefikach natnu bo eser lundibiyot,
therefore he was pierced with
ten. Lances, lances. שנאמר ויסבו עשרה אנשים נשאי כלי יואב. Sheneemar vayisbu
asara anashim nosei chlei Yoav. Ten of the men of יואב Yoav
carrying of his weapons, you know,
came and smote אבשלום. Avshalom. ולפי שגנב ג' לבבות, Ulefi sheganav gimel
levavot, here it says גניבות gneivot but the side גירסא girsa is
probably better, לבבות. levavot. He stole three hearts. לב אביו, ולב
בית דין, ולב ישראל. Lev aviv, ulev beit din, ulev Yisrael. He,
you know, he deceived everyone. שנאמר ויגנב אבשלום את
לב אנשי ישראל. Sheneemar vayignov Avshalom et lev anshei Yisrael. לפיכך נתקעו
בו ג' שבטים. Lefichach nitke'u vo gimel shevatim. Here's what you're talking
about, so therefore
these three darts were pierced into him. שנאמר ויקח שלשה
שבטים בכפו. Sheneemar vayikach shlosha shevatim bechapo. יואב Yoav took these three
darts in his hand ויקעם בלב אבשלום vayitka'em belev Avshalom in the
heart, the point being not just three but in the heart of
אבשלום. Avshalom. Okay. וכן למדה טובה. Vechen lemidah tovah.
But if this is, if you get paid back for the bad,
you get paid back for the good too. מרים המתינה למשה שעה
אחת. Miriam himtina leMoshe sha'ah achat.
מרים, Miriam, you know, hovered there for משה Moshe for a brief
period of time. שנאמר ותתצב אחותו מרחוק. Sheneemar vatitatzav achoto merachok. The
her sister, the sister hovered there. לפיכך נתעכבו לה ישראל שבעת
ימים במדבר. Lefichach nitakvu lah Yisrael shivat yamim bamidbar. Therefore the entire
nation waited for seven days before she healed. שנאמר והעם לא נסע
עד האסף מרים. Sheneemar veha'am lo nasa ad he'asof Miriam. יוסף זכה
לקבור
את אביו. Yosef zachah likvor et aviv. So יוסף Yosef merited to
bury his father, right? He brought him up from מצרים Mitzrayim back
to כנען. Kna'an. ואין באחיו גדול ממנו. Ve'ein be'achav gadol mimeno. And
he was the greatest of his brothers. שנאמר ויעל יוסף לקבור את
אביו, ויעלו עמו גם רכב גם פרשים. Sheneemar vaya'al Yosef likvor et
aviv, vaya'alu imo gam rechev gam parashim. So מי לנו גדול מיוסף
שלא נתעסק בו? Mi lanu gadol miYosef shelo nitaseik bo?
So there יוסף Yosef was the, there was nobody greater to take
care of the father. He was the greatest person of the time,
the greatest brother, whatever, and he took care of his father. So
therefore,
so, מי לנו גדול מיוסף שלא נתעסק בו אלא משה. Mi lanu
gadol miYosef shelo nitaseik bo ela Moshe.
So, who is greater than יוסף Yosef that only משה, Moshe you
know, the greatest person. So משה, Moshe. there was none greater. Okay.
That משה Moshe was the one, the greatest person of his time
took care of יוסף. Yosef. משה זכה בעצמות יוסף. Moshe zachah be'atzmot
Yosef.
Now, משה Moshe merited to bury the bones of יוסף. Yosef. ואין
בישראל גדול ממנו. Ve'ein beYisrael gadol mimeno.
And there was no one greater in ישראל Yisrael than משה. Moshe
שנאמר ויקח משה את עצמות יוסף עמו. Sheneemar vayikach Moshe et atzmot
Yosef imo. מי גדול ממשה שלא נתעסק בו אלא המקום. Mi gadol
miMoshe shelo nitaseik bo ela HaMakom. Who was greater than משה Moshe,
that the only one to take care of משה's bones was God.
שנאמר, you keep on going up, eventually you're going to get to
God. It's almost like חד גדיא Chad Gadya there, right? So שנאמר
ויקבר אותו בגיא. Sheneemar vayikbor oto bagai. So לא על משה בלבד
אמרו אלא על כל הצדיקים. Lo al Moshe bilvad amru ela al
kol hatzadikim.
Don't think that only משה gets buried by God, all righteous people
get buried by God. שנאמר והלך לפניך צדקך כבוד ה' יאספך. Sheneemar
vehalach lefanecha tzidkecha kevod Hashem ya'asfecha. And the honor of God will
gather you in at the time of death. Now it does seem
a little bit here that when it gets to the מדה כנגד
מדה midah keneged midah of הטובה, hatovah, that we're actually saying that
it gets upped a notch, right? Certainly by the case of מרים,
Miriam, one hour, seven days. Now the question is, does it also
mean to say the same here? Is it like, well, יוסף Yosef
gets buried by משה, is that going up a level or is
it parallel? You know,
you know, the greatest person in יוסף's Yosef time buried יעקב, Yaakov,
the greatest person when יוסף Yosef died, you know, took care of
יוסף. Yosef. So anyway, but there does seem a little bit, so
that might not be to the sense of upping it a level,
but the מרים Miriam seems to up it a level and that's
obviously an idea that the גמרא Gemara has very often, which is
מדת טובה מרובה ממדת פורענות. midat tovah merubah mimiddat pur'anut.
That you know the payback for good is at a higher
degree than the payback for bad. Okay, so let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן.
שמשון בעיניו מרד. Shimshon be'einav marad. שמשון Shimshon rebelled with his eyes,
so again going back to that theme of desire. Okay. So his
first really sinning was with his eyes. שנאמר ויאמר שמשון אל אביו
אותה קח לי כי היא ישרה בעיני. Sheneemar vayomer Shimshon el aviv
otah kach li ki hi yashrah be'einai. Take this woman for me
because she is, she's something I desire, what I want with my,
in my eyes. לפיכך נקרו פלשתים את עיניו. Lefichach nikru Plishtim et
einav. And therefore they pierced his eyes. שנאמר ויאחזו פלשתים וינקרו את
עיניו. Sheneemar vayochezu Plishtim vayinakru et einav. Okay. איני. Eini. Is this
really true? By the way, now we are seeing the man as
the one who is sexual sin and desiring and taking a woman.
Okay. איני. Eini. Is it? Of course, his sin was desiring non-Jewish
women,
you know,
נשים נכריות. nashim nochriyot. So again, the question about is it about
what's the man's sin here? Is it about adultery and wife? It's
not about betraying a wife, it's about the foreign women that he's
desiring. Okay. Anyway, לפיכך נקרו את עיניו שנאמר ויאחזו פלשתים וינקרו את
עיניו. Lefichach nikru et einav sheneemar vayochezu Plishtim vayinakru et einav. איני.
Eini. Is that true? והכתיב ואביו ואמו לא ידעו כי מה' הוא.
Vehachtiv ve'aviv ve'imo lo yadu ki meHashem hu. Wait, it was all,
it was all by God, right? This was all directed by God
as a way of paying back the פלשתים. Plishtim. So what are
we doing saying that he was punished? Ultimately this was all God's
hand. So the גמרא says, no. כי אזל מיהא בתר ישרותא אזל.
Ki azal miha batar yashruta azal.
He wasn't doing it to serve God's plan; he was following his
own lusts. You know, the fact that God ultimately was operating at
the same time, that doesn't get you off the hook. Obviously it
raised that whole question
about בחירה חפשית. bechirah chofshit. God
says, ועבדום וענו אתם ארבע מאות שנה. V'avadum v'inu osam arba meios
shana. So
why were the מצרים Mitzrim punished? They were just doing what God
had decreed. So there are different answers. One answer is, okay, God
decreed it, but that wasn't why they were doing it. They were
still making their own free choice. You know, another answer is, they
were a little over-enthusiastic.
God didn't say that it would be that they what? They didn't
have to enjoy it so much, they didn't have to right you
know to the degree to which they did it. But even before
saying that, it's like just because God somehow is somehow working in
parallel and it's part of God's plan doesn't get you and your
בחירה חפשית bechirah chafshis off the hook. Interesting that it's different with
יוסף Yosef here, because he's like the same story but it was
all לטובה. l'tovah. Ah, and that he does use it to get
the brothers off the hook. Right, that's a very good point. Or
at least to at least to like, you know, alleviate their anxieties.
That's an excellent point. At least he didn't just take her and
rape her like the דינה Dinah or with דוד and his sister
you know. So he asks her parents to be... Right, right, right.
It's not rape. I think the sin here more is just general
undifferentiated lust and it's foreign women and all of that. And maybe
he's a little bit of like withholding from his
total... right, right, right. That's a good point. Yeah. Okay, so it
says, okay. תניא ותנא ברייתא. Tanya v'sana baraisa. רבי אומר. Rebbe omer.
תחילת
קלקולו בעזה. Techilas kilkulo b'Aza.
His first sin was in עזה, Aza, Gaza. לפיכך לקה בעזה. Lefichach
laka b'Aza.
Okay. תחילת קלקולו. Techilas kilkulo. And therefore that's when he was, how
you know when he was smitten, it was there. תחילת קלקולו בעזה
דכתיב וילך שמשון עזתה וירא שם אשה זונה. Techilas kilkulo b'Aza d'chsiv
vayelech Shimshon Azasa vayar sham isha zona. He saw a prostitute and
he took her. לפיכך לקה בעזה דכתיב ויורידו אותו עזתה. Lefichach laka
b'Aza d'chsiv vayoridu oso Azasa. When they had him in chains, they
brought him down to עזה. Aza. The גמרא says one minute, what
do you mean his first sin was in עזה? Aza? והכתיב וירד
שמשון תמנתה. V'hachsiv vayered Shimshon Timnasa.
He went to תמנה Timna and there he took a woman and
that was before the עזה Aza the prostitute in עזה. Aza. So
the גמרא says תחילת קלקולו מיהא בעזה. Techilas kilkulo miha b'Aza. Yes,
he took a woman in עזה, Aza, but רש״י Rashi says in
תמנה Timna she'd been a foreign woman but at least he married
her. But the real first sin was in עזה Aza where he
started sleeping with prostitutes, which is interesting, right, like bringing a non-הלכה
Halacha morality into it, right? Like, okay, sleeping with non-Jewish women, sleeping
with prostitutes... no, sleeping with prostitutes is still worse, you know, than
sleeping with non-Jewish women. The תמנה, Timna, isn't that also in the
יהודה Yehuda story, the same name? Yeah, תמנה Timna is a, right,
that's a good point, that sexual encounter in תמנה. Timna. Okay, both
in the both in... Right,
right, right. Okay, היה ויהי אחרי כן ויאהב אשה בנחל שורק. Haya
vayehi acharei chen vaye'ehav isha b'nachal Sorek. Afterwards
he loved a woman in נחל שורק. Nachal Sorek. ושמה דלילה. U'shma
Delilah. תניא רבי אומר. Tanya Rebbe omer. אלמלא נקרא שמה דלילה, Ilmalei
nikra shma Delilah,
even if her name had not been דלילה, Delilah, ראויה היתה שתקרא
דלילה. re'uya haysa shetikarei Delilah. What an appropriate name this was, דלילה.
Delilah. It should have been דלילה Delilah anyway even if it had
not been. דלדלה את כחו. Dildela es kocho. She like, she like
sucked out... רש״י Rashi says דלדלה dildela means uprooted, but I think
it also means like to diminish. She diminished his strength. דלדלה את
לבו, Dildela es libo, diminished or whatever or you know uprooted his
heart. דלדלה את מעשיו, Dildela es ma'asav, diminished his deeds. דלדלה את
כחו. Dildela es kocho. Okay, so that's all, she was מדלדל. medaldel.
So now we're going to explain it. דלדלה את כחו דכתיב ויסר
כחו מעליו, Dildela es kocho d'chsiv vayasar kocho me'alav, that his strength
was sapped from him. דלדלה את לבו דכתיב ותרא דלילה כי הגיד
לה את
כל לבו. Dildela es libo d'chsiv vasere Delilah ki higid lah es
kol libo. She confided in her and she betrayed him. So she
stole his heart. She דלדלה את מעשיו דאיסתלק שכינה מיניה, dildela es
ma'asav d'istalek Shechina minei,
that she caused the divine... what does it mean his deeds? Like
his, you know, his that he had merited, that the divine presence
departed from him. דכתיב והוא לא ידע כי ה׳ סר מעליו. D'chsiv
v'hu lo yada ki Hashem sar me'alav. God had departed, he was
not aware. ותרא. Vasere. Okay, now we're going to discuss this a
little more. ותרא דלילה כי הגיד לה את כל לבו. Vasere Delilah
ki higid lah es kol libo. דלילה Delilah saw that she had...
he had opened his heart to her, told her the truth. מנא
ידעה? Mina yad'a? How'd she know? If you know the story, he
had been giving her lies before that. Where's your strength from? So
he tells her one thing and she believes him and it was
a lie, and another thing and a lie. And now he finally
tells her no, no, it's my hair, whatever. Now she saw he
told her the truth. How'd she know? Maybe it was another lie?
So אמר רבי חנין אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chanin amar Rav, ניכרין
דברי אמת. nikarin divrei emes. Such a powerful three words in the
גמרא. You can, yeah, you can tell when it's the truth. Now,
sometimes the problem is that some people are so good at lying
that we think we can tell. Oh, you know, I know, it
really held together that story, I could tell it was sincere, it
made sense or whatever. Now רש״י Rashi says part of ניכרין דברי
אמת nikarin divrei emes is that it fit the fact pattern, right?
She saw the hair. She saw he wasn't drinking wine. There was
like things that reinforced that. But you know on the other hand,
you know as as another רש״י Rashi says elsewhere on the תורה
Torah or whatever, a good way to get a lie believed is
you sprinkle in little elements of truth in it, you know? But
anyway, but okay, but sometimes, you know, things really hold together and
there are people that can always trick the lie machine, but sometimes,
you know, the lie detector. But ניכרין דברי אמת. nikarin divrei emes.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, ידעה באותו צדיק דלא מפיק שם שמים לבטלה.
yad'a b'oso tzadik d'lo mafik shem shamayim l'vatala. No,
she had another way of knowing. She knew that שמשון, Shimshon, notice
he went from being like following his lusts or whatever, now he's
a... She knew this צדיק would never say God’s name in vain.
דכיוון דאמר d'keivan d'amar since he said נזיר אלוהים אני, nezir elohim
ani, even though he didn’t use God’s name in an oath, but
he was saying this with using God’s name, אמרה השתא ודאי קושטא
קאמר, amra hashta vadai kushta ka'amar, oh, now he must be telling
the truth. Let’s read one more line. ויהי כי הציקה לו בדבריה
כל הימים ותאלצהו, vayehi ki hitzika lo bidvareha kol hayamim vate'altzehu, and
when she sort of pressured him with her words and she pressured
him, whatever, so he finally gave in and told her the truth.
מאי ותאלצהו? mai vate'altzehu? How did she pressure him? So אמר, so
אמר רבי יצחק דבי רבי אמי בשעת גמר ביאה נשמטה מתחתיו. amar
Rabbi Yitzchak d'vei Rabbi Ami besha'at gmar bi'ah nishmeta mitachtav. So getting
us back to sex, so at the time when he was about
to achieve orgasm, right, she withdrew. So she withheld sex at a
critical moment until he would finally reveal the
truth. Okay. ועתה השמרי נא אל תשתי יין ושכר ואל תאכלי כל
טמא, ve'ata hishamri na al tishti yayin veshachar ve'al tochli kol tamei,
so this is what the מלאך malach tells שמשון’s Shimshon mother, אשת
מנוח, eshet Manoach, watch yourself, don’t drink wine and don’t eat anything
that is impure. So meaning presumably non-kosher. מאי כל טמא? mai kol
tamei? What does it mean? Don’t, what’s impure? What is it? What
are we talking about? וכי עד השתא דברים טמאים אכלה? vechi ad
hashta devarim tme'im achla? What, until now she was like eating חזיר?
chazir? Like what's the point? So אמר רבי יצחק דבי רבי אמי,
amar Rabbi Yitzchak d'vei Rabbi Ami, no,
דברים
האסורים בנזיר. devarim ha'asurim benazir. No, we don't mean other דברים טמאים,
devarim tme'im, דברים טמאים devarim tme'im from a נזיר nazir perspective, not
only wine directly but
grapes and the pits and the seeds and everything we learned in
מסכת נזיר. masechet nazir. Okay, so I guess we will end here,
we will pick up with the שמשון Shimshon story tomorrow.